Guide to the Haiti Tourist Bureau photographs, 1950-1955 RL.11783
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Haiti Tourist Bureau photographs
1950-1955
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11783
0.2 Linear Feet 1 box 17 prints 8x10 inches
Collection consists of seventeen glossy 8x10 inch black-and-white photographs of tourist destinations and activities in Haiti, marked on the versos with the associated name of the Haiti Tourist Bureau in New York City, established sometime around 1950. These images served as visual components for the island's 1950s tourism campaigns, and show white tourists in various posed scenes, visiting handicraft shops and outdoor markets, riding donkeys, enjoying the beach, and watching folkloric dances. There are also several views of the capital, Port-au-Prince, and smaller towns such as Cap-Haïtien, as well as resorts, beaches, town streets, and mountainsides. Noted Haitian photographer Edouard Peloux's name appears on a print signed "Ed. Peloux, 19-7-53." The rest are unsigned and undated. Several of the photographs appear in a 1955 publication, "A Guide to Haiti, Star of the Caribbean," also by the Haiti Tourist Bureau.
Arrangement
The prints are arranged in numerical order according to the original identifiers on the print labels. There are gaps in the numbering.
Historical Note
The Haiti Tourist Bureau was established sometime around 1950 and had an office on Rockefeller Plaza. At the time the images in this collection were taken, the director was Louis Pierre-Noel, and after his departure in 1953, Hermann L. Désir. The agency seems to have been affiliated with Haiti's Office national du tourisme et de relations publique, based in Port-au-Prince, whose director at the time was Pierre Chauvet.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Haiti Tourist Bureau photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2019.
Content Description
Collection consists of seventeen glossy 8x10 inch black-and-white photographs of tourist destinations and activities in Haiti, marked on the versos with the associated name of the Haiti Tourist Bureau in New York City, established sometime around 1950. These images served as visual components for the island's 1950s tourism campaigns, and show white tourists in various posed scenes, visiting handicraft shops and outdoor markets, riding donkeys, enjoying the beach, and watching folkloric dances. There are also several views of the capital, Port-au-Prince, and smaller towns such as Cap-Haïtien, as well as resorts, beaches, town streets, and mountainsides. Noted Haitian photographer Edouard Peloux's name appears on a print signed "Ed. Peloux, 19-7-53." The rest are unsigned and undated. Several of the photographs appear in a 1955 publication, "A Guide to Haiti, Star of the Caribbean," also by the Haiti Tourist Bureau.
Advertising -- Tourism; Tourism -- Haiti; Tourists -- Haiti -- Photographs; Travel Photography; Haiti -- Description and travel; Haiti -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints
- Tourism campaign photographs, 1950-1955
  - Kenscoff Mountain Resort, 8,000 feet above see level at one hour from Port-au-Prince, Haiti - Visitors and vegetable vendors, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0001)
    Scope and Contents
    Legacy identifier: #1
  - Popular Market in Haiti - Visitors buying straw hats, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0002)
    Legacy identifier: #2
  - Mahogany handicrafts in Haiti - Salad Bowls and lazy suzanne, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0003)
    Legacy identifier: #3. A version of this photograph, taken minutes apart during the same shoot, appears in A Guide to Haiti, Star of the Caribbean, page 60.
  - Handicraft in Haiti - Woodcarving - Sculptures and voodoo drums, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0004)
    Legacy identifier: #4. This image appears in the Guide to Haiti, page 59.
  - Handicraft in Haiti - Straws articles, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0005)
    Legacy identifier: #6. This image appears in the Guide to Haiti, page 59.
  - Typical dress - made in Haiti, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0006)
    Legacy identifier: #9
  - Beach "Raymond les Bains" in Jacmel, Haiti, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0007)
    Legacy identifier: #10. A cropped version of this beach scene is shown on page 47 of the Guide to Haiti.
  - Ruins of Sans Souci Palace, built in Milet, Haiti by King Henry Christophe, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0008)
    Legacy identifier: #12
  - Port-au-Prince, view from the mountain, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0009)
    Legacy identifier: #14
  - Kenscoff Mountain Resort - In foreground visitors and vegetable plantation, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0010)
    Legacy identifier: #18
  - Cap-Haitien, Second City of Haiti [by Edouard Peloux], 1953 July 19 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0011)
    Legacy identifier: #19. This long aerial view of Cap Haitien and its beachfront, is signed on the print, lower right, "Ed. Peloux/19-7-53" (July 19, 1953). Edouard Peloux (1901-1994) was a well-known Haitian photographer.
  - Folk Dansers in Haiti, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0012)
    Legacy identifier: #21
  - Folk Dance in Haiti, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0013)
    Legacy identifier: #28
  - Beach near Cap-Haitien, Haiti, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0014)
    Legacy identifier: #29
  - Coastal boats in Port-au-Prince, Haiti, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0015)
    Legacy identifier: #30
  - Palm square on the Exposition Ground, Port-au-Prince, Haiti, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0016)
    Legacy identifier: #32
  - Port-au-Prince, Haiti / Midtown, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0017)
    Unnumbered print. This aerial view of the city includes three World-War II era planes in flight in the foreground, flanking the photographer's plane. Several physical differences, such as handwritten instead of typed captions, set it apart from the rest of the prints.